Guide to the International Center for Transitional Justice (ICTJ) Records, 1981-2008
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
- Geographic Series, 1981-2007, (24 boxes)
  - Europe, 1994-2006, (2 boxes)
    - Bosnia and Herzegovina
      - Cibelli, Kristen and Tamy Guberek. Justice Unknown, Justice Unsatisfied? Bosnian NGOs Speak about the International Criminal Tribunal for the Former Yugoslavia. Boston: Education for Public Inquiry and International Citizenship, Tufts University, 2002
      - O'Donoghue, Lynne and Alma Dedic, eds. Early Justice and Truth in Bosnia and Herzegovina: Public Perceptions. Sarajevo: United Nations Development Programme, 2005
      - The Court of Bosnia and Herzegovina. Project Implementation Plan Progress Report. October 2004
      - The Court of Bosnia and Herzegovina. Update on the Progress of the War Crimes Project. January 2005
      - OSCE Mission to Bosnia and Herzegovina. War Crimes Trials before the Domestic Courts of Bosnia and Herzegovina: Progress and Obstacles. OSCE Mission to Bosnia and Herzegovina, 2005
    - Czech Republic
      - American Bar Association Central and East European Law Initiative. Concept Paper on Issues of Criminal Procedure for the Czech Republic. Washington, DC: CEELI, 1994
    - Germany
      - Der Enquete-Kommission. Leben in der DDR, Leben nach 1989-Aufarbeitung und Versönung. Band I. Schwerin: Landtag Mecklenburg-Vorpommern, 1996 (Box 22)
      - The Federal Government. Action Plan: Civilian Crisis Prevention, Conflict Resolution and Post-Conflict Peace-Building. Berlin: German Federal Government, 2004
      - Zurof, Dr. Efraim. Worldwide Investigation and Prosecution of Nazi War Criminals (April 1, 2004-March 31, 2005): An Annual Status Report. Jerusalem: Simon Wiesenthal Center-Israel, 2005
    - Kosovo
      - American Bar Association Central and East European Law Initiative. Political Killings in Kosova/Kosovo, March-June 1999. Washington, DC: CEELI, 2000
      - Baldwin, Clive. Minority Rights in Kosovo under International Rule. London: Minority Rights Group International, 2006
      - Department of Human Rights and Rule of Law, Legal System Monitoring Section. Protection of Witnesses in the Criminal Justice System (March 2002-April 2003). OSCE Mission in Kosovo
    - Northern Ireland
      - Journal Issues, 2005-2007
        Contains Healing Through Remembering work and a section of the International and Comparative Law Quarterly
      - Other Publications, 1995-2006
        Contains work on the Healing Through Remembering Project, socio-economic rights, loyalist paramilitary murders, truth recovery and the war on terror
    - Serbia
      - Ilic, Dejan and Veran Matic. Truths, Responsibilities, Reconciliations: The Example of Serbia. Belgrade: SAMIZDAT/Free B92, 2000
      - Seymour, Jack M. and James S. Henderson. Fostering Regional Cooperation and Reconciliation in Serbia and Southeastern Europe. Policy Bulletin (Oct. 2002)
      - Orentlicher, Diane. Shrinking the Space for Denial: The Impact of the ICTY in Serbia. Washington, DC: Open Society Justice Initiative, 2008
    - Spain
      - Thieux, Laurence. El terrorismo internacional: causas e implicaciones estrategicas. Madrid: Centro de Investigacion Para la Paz, 2005
      - Bustelo, Mabel Gonzalez. Terrorismo y democracia: Espana y los atentados del 11-M. Madrid: Centro de Investigacion Para la Paz, 2005
    - Swizterland
      - Bleeker, Mo and Jonathan Sisson, eds. Dealing with the Past: Critical Issues, Lessons Learned, and Challenges for Future Swiss Policy. Bern: Swiss Peace, 2004
  - Middle East, 2000-2007, (2 boxes)
    - Multi-Country/Regional
      - Waage, Hilde Henriksen. Norwegians? Who Needs Norwegians?: Explaining the Oslo Back Channel: Norway's Political Past in the Middle East. Oslo: Royal Norwegian Ministry of Foreign Affairs, 2000 (Box 22)
    - Iran
      - Boroumand, Laden and Roya Boroumand. Illusion and Reality of Civil Society in Iran: An Ideological Debate. Social Research 67.2 (Summer 2000): 303-344
    - Iraq
      Contains work on security options pre-invasion, civilian casualties, how religious and ethnic relations shape the constitution, and how to establish a stable democratic state. Work primarily produced by the United States Institute of Peace and Minority Rights Group International
    - Palestine/Israel
      - Preliminary Submission of the Palestine Liberation Organization to the International Commission of Inquiry. December 8, 2000 (Box 23)
      - Sharm el-Sheikh Fact-Finding Committee. Report. April 30, 2001
  - North America, 2002-2007, (4.5 boxes)
    - Haiti
      - Bryan, Elizabeth, Cynthia Arnson, José Raúl Perales, and Johanna Mendelson Forman Governance and Security in Haiti: Can the International Community Make a Difference? Washington, DC: Woodrow Wilson International Center for Scholars, 2007 (Box 23)
    - Mexico
      - Benítez-Manaut, Raúl. Mexico and the New Challenges of Hemispheric Security. Washington, DC: Woodrow Wilson International Center for Scholars, 2004 (Box 23-26)
      - Freeman, Laurie. State of Siege: Drug-Related Violence and Corruption in Mexico: Unintended Consequences of the War on Drugs. Washington, DC: Washington Office on Latin America, 2006
      - Procuraduria General de la Republica. Averiguación Previa: PGR/FEMOSPP/002/2002. Inculpados: Luis Echeverría Álvarez, Julio Sánchez Vargas, Luis Gutiérrez Oropeza, Luis de la Barreda Moreno, Miguel Nazar Haro, Raúl Mendiolea Zerecero, Javier Vázquez Félix, y Salvador del Toro Rosales. Delito: Genocidio y privación ilegal de la libertad en su modalidad de plagio o secuestro. Consignación: sin deteniro., (32 folders)
    - Canada
      - Journal Issues, 2002
        Contains one issue from the Human Rights Research and Education Bulletin
      - Other Publications, 2002-2003
        Consists primarily of work by the Aboriginal Healing Foundation on residential schools, survivors of the Canadian residential school system, aboriginal sex offending, and a report on the Aboriginal Healing Foundation itself.
    - United States
      - Journal Issues, 2000-2002 (Box 27)
        Four issues from Teaching Tolerance Magazine.
      - Other Publications, 1997-2007
        Includes works on human rights, education, the war on terror, the 1898 Wilmington Race Riot and the ensuing Truth and Reconciliation Commission.
  - South and Central America, 1981-2007, (11 boxes)
    - Multi-Country/Regional
      - Journal Issues, 2003-2006 (Box 28)
        Issues from the Latin American Studies Association, LASA Forum, and Kawsaq
      - Woodrow Wilson Center Update on the Americas, 2002-2007
        Contains information on China's presence in Latin America, the issues of integration and fragmentation, MERCOSUR, security, judicial reform, social reform, and new populist and leftist movements.
      - Other Publications, 2000-2007
        Includes productions from the Washington Office on Latin America, the Columbia University Institute of Latin American Studies, and the Centro de Derechos Humanos about human rights, conflict situations, enhancing judicial independence, and U.S. military programs in Latin America.
    - Argentina
      - Organización Institucional y Contenidos del Futuro Museo de la Memoria. Las Organizaciones de Derechos Humanos, 2000 (Box 29)
      - El Derecho a la Verdad: Desarollo en el Ambito Internacional y en la Republica Argentina.
      - El largo camino de los Derechos Humanos en la Argentina democrática.
      - Quintana, Tomás Ojea and Gustavo Gioseffi Derechos y Participación: Guía para la Capacitación-Acción. Buenos Aires: Fundación Foro por los Derechos de la Niñez, 2005
      - Poder Ejecutivo Nacional. Comisión Nacional sobre la Desaparición de Personas, 1983
      - Puentes Magazine
        One copy, December 2007
    - Brazil
      Includes works primarily about human rights violations, produced within Brazil.
      - Centre on Housing Rights and Evictions. Human Rights in Brazil, Gross Inequalities and Inconsistencies: Mission Report. Geneva: COHRE, 2003.
      - Centro de Referência sobre a Repressâo Política no Brasil (1964-1985). Rio de Janeiro/Sâo Paulo, 2005.
      - CONARQ. Legislaçâo Arquivís Tica Brasileira Conselho Nacional de Arquivos. Rio de Janeiro: CONARQ, 2004.
      - Comissâo de Direitos Humanos da ONU. Politica Externa e Direitos Humanos
      - Republica Federativa do Brasil. Constituiçâo Universal dos Direitos Humanos. Sâo Paulo: Estado de Sâo Paulo.
    - Chile
      - Centro de Derechos Humanos. Anuario de Derechos Humanos, 2006. Santiago: Universidad de Chile, 2006 (Box 30-31)
      - Oficina Nacional de Retorno (National Office of Return) binders, 1990-1993
        Contains monthly reports, comments on international conferences, coordination of institutions working on exile-return, and information on special investigations
      - Historia de la Ley binders, 1992-2001, (12 folders)
        Consists of reports on several laws relating to programs for Chilean exiles and returnees, including the establishment of a self-employment program, provisional benefits, exemptions for taxes, the modification of the customs tariff, and amnesty.
      - Salud binders, 1994-2002
        Includes information on the health care system and the care of persons affected by political state repression
      - Reconciliation binders, 1986-2002
        Information primarily relates to reparations and reconciliation, but also on torture and the Ministry of Justice. Newspaper clippings included.
    - Colombia
      - Publications, 2004-2006 (Box 32)
        Consists of work from the Colombian government, the UN, and NGOs. The focus is on establishing peace, reintegrating demobilized combatants, freedom of expression, and human rights in general.
    - Cuba
      - Desafío (Box 33)
        Three issues, dating from April to August, 2002
      - Stanton, Kimberly, eds. Retreat from Reason: U.S.-Cuban Academic Relations and the Bush Administration. Washington, DC: Latin America Working Group Education Fund, 2006
    - Ecuador
      - Stanton, Kimberly, eds. Informe Alternativo: Derechos Económicos, Sociales, y Culturales. Quito, Ecuador: Centro de Derechos Económicos y Sociales, 2001
    - Guatemala
      - Publications, 1981-2004 (Box 34)
        Contains reports on sexual violence, the penal code, sovereignty five years after peace accords and Ordenes Generales documents
      - Dictamen, 1993-2001, (20 folders)
        Chiefly centers on anthropological forensic investigations in particular areas of Guatemala.
    - Perú
      - Journal Issues, 1999-2006 (Box 35-37)
        Contains issues from six different journals, predominantly Ideele, with focus on human rights, democracy, and the judicial system
      - Comisión de la Verdad y Reconciliación materials, 1999-2006
        Includes work on education, justice, peacebuilding, and bulletins from the Comisión
      - Asociación Pro Derechos Humanos, 1998-2002
        Consists of publications addressing human rights abuses, including displacement and violence directed at women. Several documents derive information by testimonials.
      - Other Publications, 2001-2005
        Contains work primarily on human rights and democracy, predominantly produced within Perú. Notable international organizations include Oxfam, the Organization of American States, and the Washington Office on Latin America
    - Venezuela
      - The Carter Center. The Carter Center and the Peacebuilding Process in Venezuela, June 2002-February 2005. Summary. Atlanta: The Carter Center, 2005 (Box 38)
      - The Carter Center. Observing the Venezuela Presidential Recall Referendum: Comprehensive Report. Atlanta: The Carter Center, 2005
- Oversize Material, (3 boxes, 1 folder)
  - Geographic Series
    Contains major newspapers from multiple countries, political posters, and journals. Material is arranged alphabetically be country and is arranged further chronologically.
    - Afghanistan newspaper, 2003 (Box 39)
    - Colombia poster, 2005 (Box 39)
    - East Timor (Box 39)
      - Journal Nacional Seanário, 2005
      - East Timor Truth and Reconciliation posters (Opaperfolder 1)
    - Germany poster celebrating democracy (Opaperfolder 1)
    - Ghana newspapers, 2002-2005 (Box 39-41)
    - Kenya transitional justice poster (Box 40)
    - Liberia War poster (Opaperfolder 1)
    - Perú publications, 1984 and 2003 (Box 40)
    - Sierra Leone newspapers, 2002 and 2004 (Box 40)
    - Zimbabwe newspapers, 2002 (Box 41)
    - Latin American poster [date and subject unidentified] (Opaperfolder 1)
- Accession (2009-0193), (76 boxes)
  Accession (2009-0193) (76 lin. ft) includes country files, staff files, audiovisual materials, the Mena survey, ICTJ publications, miscellaneous publications, institutional materials, CPU materials, Documentation Center materials, Historical Memory Project and Policymakers Retreat files, and other miscellaneous materials.
  RESTRICTED. For more information, contact the reference archivist.
  - Country files-Africa (Box 1)
    - Agreement between GOS and SPLM/SPLA, Sudan
    - Report of the International Commission of Inquiry on Darfur to UN Secretary General
    - The Zimbabwe HR NGO Forum, March 26, 2001
    - Zimbabwe
    - Uganda assessment and documents
    - Sierra Leone
    - Nigeria
    - Sierra Leone
    - Rwanda
    - Nigeria (includes Civilian Oversight)
    - Journal publications-Nigeria
    - NRC-Ghana
    - TRC and child soldiers in Sierra Leone
    - Nigeria
    - Liberia News and other documents
    - Liberia background
    - Liberia critical documents (Box 2)
    - Sierra Leone
    - Rwanda
    - South Africa (2 folders)
    - Eritea-Internal
    - Origins of Conflict
    - UN documents
    - Sierra Leone in the news
    - Sierra Leone TRC
    - Toronto Star, SLE Special Report, Dec. 15, 2001
    - Sierra Leone
    - PRI Reports
    - PRI Reports: Rwanda
    - Rwanda: News updates
    - Sierra Leone Truth Commission
    - TRC in South Africa and Sierra Leone
    - UNAMSIL TRC reports
    - Special Court
    - Independent Observer: Sam Hinga Norman fires lawyers (SLE), June 4, 2004
    - Ethiopia: Prosecutions (binder)
    - S. Ct. Indictments
    - Silencing Sexual Violence: recent developments in the CDF Case at the Special Court for Sierra Leone (Box 3)
    - Publication of SL Bar Association
    - Sierra Leone (9 folders)
    - Uganda (3 folders)
    - Ghana
    - Eritrea and Ethiopia (Box 4)
    - Berundi
    - Liberia
    - Nigeria
    - Zimbabwe
    - Constitution of Zimbabwe
    - South Africa
    - Rwanda
    - Democratic Republic of Congo
    - Kenya
    - Morocco
    - Sudan
    - Articles on miscellaneous African countries
    - Articles on multiple African countries (2 folders)
    - International Criminal Law: A Discussion Guide
    - Materials on TRC
    - Miscellaneous articles, notes, etc.
  - Country files-Asia (Box 5)
    - Sri Lanka (includes Intelligence Oversight Mechanisms)
    - Sri Lanka
    - South Asia
    - Assistance to Justice and the Rule of Law in Afghanistan (bound volume), Feb. 2004
    - Documents on the Sri Lankan Peace Process (binder)
    - Newsletter of National Peace Council of Sri Lanka, Sept. 2009
    - Pakistan
    - Russia
    - Bangladesh: Intelligence Oversight Mechanisms
    - India (2 folders)
    - Burma (2 folders)
    - Taiwan
    - Philippines
    - Japan
    - AFG-Background documents (4 folders)
    - Critical documents on Afghanistan
    - AFG-UN Mapping Report (Box 6)
    - Afghanistan (2 folders)
    - Critical documents on EC (Cambodia)
    - Cambodia: News reports on EC
    - Documents on EC
    - Cambodia (3 folders)
    - Indonesia (2 folders)
    - East Timor (2 folders)
    - East Timor-Methodology
    - East Timor-Judicial System Monitoring Reports
    - East Timor (3 folders)
    - Iraq
  - Country files-Europe (Box 7)
    - Sweden
    - United Kingdom (includes Oversight Mechanisms)
    - Serbia (includes Belgrade)
    - Federal Republic of Yugoslavia
    - Bosnia
    - Bosnia and Herzigovina
    - Kosovo (2 folders)
    - United Kingdom
    - Rumania
    - Germany (2 folders)
    - Czech Republic
    - Former Yugoslavia
    - Armenia
    - Latvia
    - Articles on multiple countries
  - Country files-South America (Box 8)
    - Intelligence (includes Intelligence Reform: Guatamala)
    - Guatamala (2 folders)
    - Guatamala, Ghana, Peru-Methodology
    - Chile (includes Comision Etica Contra la Tortura)
    - El Salvador
    - Columbia
    - Peru
    - Argentina
    - Intelligence Reform/Spain
    - Brasil (3 folders)
    - Chile
    - Paraguay
    - Materials on miscellaneous South American countries (2 folders)
  - Staff Files: Louis Bickford (Box 9)
    Director, Policy Makers and Civil Society Unit (PCSU), New York. Employed 2001-present (2009).
    - ICTJ Conference, Children and Truth Commissions: Expert Discussion, March 26, 2007
    - Thailand
    - Angola
    - Sudan
    - Columbia
    - ICTJ Justice and Peace Project-Algeria
    - Nepal
    - Kosovo
    - Sri Lanka
    - Indonesia and Chile
    - Uganda
    - Chad
    - DRC
    - Burundi
    - Films and concerts
    - Song lyrics
    - Materials on Chad
    - Peace talks world wide: possible case studies, annotated
    - Materials on Columbia
    - Peace Negotiations Watch, Vol. IV, no. 5, March 8 2007
    - Materials on Liberia
    - Materials on Sierra Leone
    - Articles on Uganda
    - Articles on Japan
    - Materials on Rwanda
    - Articles on Nepal
    - Social and cosmopolitan liberalism, by C.R. Beitz
    - ICTJ Intern Guidelines
    - Guantanamo Bay detention camp (Wikipedia entry)
    - US Institute of Peace, The Aceh Peace Process
    - Global Conflict Panorama, 2006
    - Conflict Barometer 2006, by HIIK
    - Materials on India
    - ICTJ: Documentations, Archives, and Knowledge Management
    - Unit Program Budgets for 2008
    - The Justice Crusade and the Impact of Human Rights Trials in Latin America
    - La 'guistizia di transizione': international law principio del duty to prosecute come una nuova variabile
    - Articles on Germany
    - Materials on Morroco
    - The Comunal Violence (Prevention, Control, and Rehabilitation of Victims) Bill, 2005
    - Engendering Wartime Conflict: Women and War Trauma, CSVR
    - Articles on Kashmir
    - Children in the Ranks: the Maoists Use of Child Soldiers in Nepal, HR Watch
    - Materials on Afghanistan
    - Italian vocabulary
    - Articles on South Africa
    - Materials on Sudan
    - Materials related to Piero Sullo
    - Multiple-country overview and summary reports
    - Graphs on Peace Agreements in Armed Conflicts, 1989-2005
    - Materials on miscellaneous workshops, conferences, and talks
    - Materials from the UN on HR, TJ, and Peacebuilding
    - Materials on the Human Rights Council
    - Ex-combatants/State of the Art DDR
    - Preliminary notes on the FP 7 project proposal
    - Materials on miscellaneous countries
    - Miscellaneous articles
    - Miscellaneous notes
  - Mena Survey (Box 10-11)
  - Media materials (Box 12)
  - Media 1 (Box 13)
  - ICTJ Publications (Box 14)
    - Case Studies
      - Accountability in Argentina: 20 years later, transitional justice maintains momentum. August 2005.
      - Bosnia and Herzigovina: selected developments in transitional justice. October 2004.
      - Serbia and Montenegro: selected developments in transitional justice. October 2004.
      - The Sierra Leone Truth and Reconciliation Commission: reviewing the first year. January 2004.
      - The Special Court for Sierra Leone: the first eighteen months. March 2004.
    - Conference Reports
      - Magarrell, L. and B. Gutierrez. Lessons in truth-seeking: international experiences informing United States initiatives. September 2006.
    - Gender Justice
      - Nesiah, Vasuki. Truth commissions and gender: principles, policies, and procedures. July 2006
      - Nesiah, Vasuki. Comisiones de la verdad y genero: principios, politicas y procedimientos. July 2006
      - Nesiah, Vasuki. Les commissions de verite et la dimension de genre: principes, politiques et procedures. July 2006
    - Occassional Papers
      - Birks, Teresa. Neglected duty: providing comprehensive preapartions to the Indonesian '1965 Victims' of state persecution. July 2006.
      - Borello, Federico. A few first steps: the long road to a just peace in the Democratic Republic of Congo. October 2004.
      - Borello, Federico. Les premiers pas: la longue route vers une paix juste en Republique du Congo. Octobre 2004.
      - Bosire, Lydiah. Overpromised, underdelivered: transitional justice in Sub-Saharan Africa. July 2006.
      - Clarke, R., G. Wandita and Samsidar. Considering victims: the Aceh peace process from a transitional justice perspective. January 2008.
      - Cohen, David. Intended to fail: the trials before the ad hoc human rights court in Jakarta. August 2003.
      - Cohen, David. Intended to fail: the trials before the ad hoc human rights court in Jakarta. July 2004.
      - Cohen, David. Intended to fail: the trials before the ad hoc human rights court in Jakarta. Undated.
      - Cruvellier, Thierry and Marta Valina. Croatia: selected developments in transistional justice. December 2006.
      - Cruvellier, Thierry and Marta Valina. Hrvatska: razvoj dogadanja u oblasti tranzicijske pravade. December 2006
      - Farice, H. & R. Simarmata. The Struggle for truth and justice: a survey of transitional justice initiatives throughout Indonesia. January 2004.
      - Hirst, M. Too much friendship, too little truth...the commission of truth and friendship in Indonesia and Timor-Leste. January 2008.
      - ICTJ. Truth commissions and NGOs: the essential relationship. April 2004.
      - ICTJ and Human Rights Center, UC-Berkeley. Iraqi voices: attitudes toward transitional justice and social reconstruction. May 2004.
      - Pigou, Piers. Crying without tears: in pursuit of justice and reconciliation in Timor-Leste. August 2003.
      - Seils, Paul and Marieke Weirda. The International Criminal Court and conflict mediation. June 2005.
      - Valji, Nahla. Ghana's National Reconcilation Commission: a commarative assessment. September 2006.
      - Williams, Rhodri C. The contemporary right to property restitution in the context of transitional justice. May 2007
    - Prosecution Case Studies
      - ICTJ. Against the current-war crimes prosecutions in Serbia (2007).
      - ICTJ. Uprkos okolnostima: krivicni postupci za ratne zlocine u Srbiji (2007).
      - Perriello, Tom and Marieke Wierda. Lessons from the Development of Interntional Judges and Prosecutors in Kosovo. March 2006.
      - Perriello, Tom. The Special Court for Sierra Leone under scrutiny. March 2006.
      - Reiger, Caitlin and Marieke Weirda. The serious crimes process in Timor-Leste: in retrospect. March 2006.
    - Annual Reports
      - 2001-2002.
      - 2002-2003.
      - 2002-2003. (French)
      - 2002-2003. (Spanish)
      - 2003-2004.
      - 2003-2004. (French)
      - 2003-2004 (Spanish)
      - 2003-2004. (Arabic)
      - 2004-2005.
      - 2006-2007.
      - Annual Report 2008 and promotional materials
    - Books (Box 15)
      - Baldo, Suliman and Lisa Magarrell. Reparation and the Darfur peace process: ensuring victims' rights. (Arabic)
      - De Greiff, Pablo and Roger Duthie, eds. Transitional Justice and Development: Making Connections. 2009.
      - Dian, Catalina, ed. Raparaciones para las victimas de la violencia politica. 2008
      - El Centro Internacional para la Justicia Transicional. Ensayos sobre la justicia transicional. 2003
      - Freeman, Mark. Truth Commissions and Procedural Fairness. 2006.
      - Haniffa, Farzana. In the Pursiut of Democracy in Post-Colonial Sri Lanka: Local Human Rights Approaches to Transitional Justice. 2006.